All right, folks. Let's begin. Actually,
let me wait 10 or 15 seconds more so we
get more students in class. Another
thing
All right.
So, we're going to continue the series
of lectures on training neural networks.
Does anybody remember what the last
thing we discussed was? The very last
thing. Anyone?
What was the last thing we discussed?
somebody
cross entropy loss we're speaking of
losses and such like
eventually we're speaking of empirical
risk minimization how you train a
network so you're given a training set
of input output pairs each training
instance consists of the input features
and the desired output of the network
the network itself operates on this
input and computes some out some output
f which is a function of the parameters
w of the network. We compute a
divergence between the desired output of
the network and the actual output of the
network and we compute a loss which is
the average divergence over the entire
training set. And since the divergence
is depends on the function the network
and the network is a function of the
network parameters. It turns out that
the loss is also a function of network
parameters and we're going to learn the
network parameters w to minimize this
loss. Uh
we're going to minimize this loss and
we're going to use this using gradient
descent. So we're going to spend some
more time on this a lot more time on
this but first some notation. We're
going to assume a layered network. The
input to the network is what we call the
zero layer. The output of the iat layer
of the network is going to be
represented by a sup of the kth layer of
the network is going to be represented
by a superscript k and for convenience
of notation we're going to say that the
output of the zero layer is the same as
the input
and uh the output of the final layer of
course is just the output of the network
itself. We're going to have to represent
all the weights and biases. So uh the
weight of
uh which connects the ayat neuron say
the first neuron output of the first
neuron
of the first layer to say the second
of the second layer is going to be
represented as w 1 2 1. Here the first
index represents the source. The second
index represents the destination.
And the superscript here,
this one, this represents the layer
number. So that's the notation we're
going to use. Every neuron also has a
bias. So the bias corresponding to the
second neuron of the second layer will
be represented as B2.
So this two over here means it's a
second neuron. the superscript two means
it's a second layer. So uh is that
notation clear to everybody? The
notation
anyone? Okay, simple. All right. And so
here's the gradient descent approach.
The loss is a function of network
parameters. So you're going to
initialize the network parameters
somehow and then we iterate through the
gradient descent process where at each
step we adjust the current estimate of
the network parameters to take a step
against the gradient of the loss
function computed at the current value.
And does anybody remember why we take a
step against the gradient? Why do we
take a step against the gradient like
so? Anybody? Why do we do that?
anyone
why specifically the gra?
So why specifically the gradient? The
gradient points opposite to the points
to the direction the steepest ascent. So
this is the direction in which you the
function decreases fastest. That's why
we choose the gradient and we keep doing
this till the loss saturates.
So taking taking a look further, the
loss is the average of the divergences
of the uh training instances
and each training gradient descent
basically means that each parameter is
going to be adjusted against the
derivative of the loss with respect to
that parameter. If the derivative is
basically this says that move the
parameter in the direction in which the
loss will decrease as we saw in the last
class. So that means we need to be able
to estimate this derivative of the loss
with respect to the parameter.
Now the loss of course is the average of
the divergences over the training set.
So the derivative of the loss with
respect to the parameter is going to be
the average of the derivatives of the
divergences for the individual instances
with respect to the parameter. This is
just a property of derivatives. And so
we're going to have to be able to
estimate this term which is the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to the network parameter. And
that is what this class is going to be
all about. So this clear so far? Yes.
Yes or no? Everything we've said so far.
Okay. Uh and all right. So if I stay
with that, let me continue.
Now we're going to go back and just look
at calculus. A quick calculus refresher.
How do you understand the term
derivative? Again, how do you understand
the term derivative? We mentioned this
in the last class, but how do you
understand the term derivative? Anybody?
Rate of change, instantaneous rate of
change. But that's not what I said,
right? Remember how we explained the
derivative?
So the derivative we said was the
multiplicative term that m multiplies a
small increment in x to give you the
corresponding increment in y. It's a
ratio of how a small increment in x
increases y. It's not quite a ratio.
It's a multiplicative term. We can't use
the term ratio because this term could
be a vector. Is does everybody remember
this?
We're going to use this extensively.
Does everybody remember this?
Okay,
I don't know about everybody, but I got
like two or three thumbs ups, so I'll go
with that. Now,
I'm going to introduce a notation,
something called the influence diagram.
If I say y equals f ofx, then x
influences y. Every time you change x, y
gets changed.
So, I can draw an arrow between x and y.
Now on top of the arrow I'm going to
give this arrow a weight which is the
derivative of y with respect to x. And
so this is a standard graph notation
for any
delta x going into this edge. The
corresponding delta y is simply a
multiplication of this delta x by the by
the uh weight of the edge. And so this
notation, this influence diagram
captures the derivative relationship. Is
this picture clear to everybody? Yes or
no?
Okay. So now I have this other function
which is a function of many variables.
What would the corresponding influence
diagram be? Anyone? What would the
corresponding influence diagram be?
someone.
What is the entrance diagram going to be
like
anyone?
Circle.
What will it be like?
All x's, one arrow for each input. Thank
you, Anderson. So, I'd have x1, x2.
These are all the variables that
influence the influence Y, right? So,
I'm going to have arrows from all of
these guys to Y. Is this picture making
sense to all of you?
This one make sense to all of you? Yes.
Clear, right? And so that's what it's
going to be like. That's going to be the
influence diagram. What will the
derivative diagram be?
What is the what is the derivative
diagram going to be like over here?
anyone?
What's it going to be like?
All the edges will have partial
derivatives because the edge tells you
how much perturbing the input or terms
the output, right? And now using your
standard graph rules, what is delta y
going to be
over here? What is delta y going to be?
Anybody?
Summation, right? Delta Y equ= delta x1
*
partial of y with respect to x1
plus delta x2 * partial of y with
respect to x2 and so on. You're going to
sum over all of these terms, right? And
so this gives you
this the relationship
and uh you can see how y depends on how
the derivative of y depends on the
derivatives with respect to all the
variables. Now here's another one right
I have a nested function y = f of g of
x. So X influences G. G influences Y.
This picture making sense to everybody
over here?
Okay. What will the derivatives be?
What will the derivatives be over?
Anyone?
What are the derivatives going to be?
this. Let's go back and actually write
the derivatives down.
This edge is going to have the
derivative of y with respect to g. This
edge is going to have the derivative of
g with respect to x. Right? This picture
making sense? This one.
Is this one making sense? It's important
that you understand it.
So now you can see how this works.
Right? From this portion of it, I know
that delta y equals delta g * dy / dg.
From this portion of the diagram, I can
see that delta g equals delta x * dg /
dx.
So plugging the the value for delta G in
out here into this one, I'm going to get
delta y equals delta y / delta g dy /
dg*
dg / dx * delta x. But then I know that
delta y equals the derivative of y with
respect to x * delta x. So just
comparing these two you end up with a
chain rule that dy / dx = dy / dg * dj /
dx. This making sense this picture
and the explanation here. Did that make
sense to all of you?
Right? Very easy. Okay. And now I'm
going to give you
something more complex. Y is a function
of many G's but each of the G's in term
is a function of X. What is this
influence diagram going to look like?
What's this going to look like?
Anyone?
dx is just a very small very very small
delta x. So what is this inference
diagram going to look like? Anybody?
I'll wait five seconds before I answer
you myself. So, anyone
apply the chain rule? They're just
giving you the chain rule. The actual
diagram is going to look like this. X
influences all the G's.
All the G's influence Y.
Is this picture making sense
over here?
Okay. And what are the edges? So I'm
going to call just for notation I'm
going to say g1 of x= z1 g2 of x= z2 and
so on. So what will the derivatives be
each edge is going to get have the
partial derivatives
for the variables on either end of the
edge. So this edge has it weight
derivative dy / dz1. This is dy over
dz2. This is dy over dzn. And this age
this dz1 / dx, dz2 / dx and so on. This
making sense? Is this making sense to
everybody? This picture
right?
Okay. So based on this picture, what is
the derivative rule that relates y to x?
What is the derivative rule that relates
y to x? the derivative of y with respect
to x,
you're going to have to sum over all
these edges. Correct? So you're going to
get
this guy
delta y equals summation of all of these
guys of dy over dz i time delta zi.
Right? But delta zi equals dx * dz i /
dx. So you incorporate the two and you
get dy / dx= dy over dz i dz1 plus dz1 /
dx plus dy / dz dz2 plus * dz2 over dx
and so on. You sum over all incoming
paths. This is the distributed chain
rule. Everybody good with this? You
remember all of this guys?
Yes.
Okay, thumbs up, thumbs down. Did this
make sense to everybody?
Okay, so over here, I just plugged in
this one. What happens to delta x? If I
plug in this formula out here, you're
going to get delta y equals summation i
dyi over dzi
* dzi
over dxi
time delta x which is what gives us this
rule. Did that answer your question?
>> Yes.
Okay, so we're good.
And so here is the calculus refresher
for any nested function L= F of Y where
Y= G of Z DL / DZ a is going to be DL /
DY * DY / DZ and for
f equals so uh gene let's take this
until after class because that can take
a little time for basically delta x is
the same as dx I just used a slightly
fatter notation
So for any function L= F of several Z's
where each Z is a function of X you get
the distributed table where DL / DX is
the sum over all variables of DL / DZ *
DZ / DX. These are the T2 rules we're
going to keep using. So that leads us to
our first poll
which Ouch.
Okay, 10 seconds.
They're very easy pictures or questions.
Let me end the poll.
Anybody
want to answer the first question? True
or false?
Answer to the first question.
Second one,
which of the first two both are true,
right? So all statements are true.
Fantastic. So now our problem today is
how do I compute the derivative of the
divergence with respect to any
individual weight of the network?
to explain this first I'm going to start
off with a very tiny illustrative
network because we need pictures so I'm
going to use a two input one output
network this is only for illustration
right and uh
then
furthermore within each of these nodes
represents a neuron and within each
neuron so gene the question I I'll get
to that question after class just hang
on simply because we'll take some time
on that I have a lot to cover So each of
these nodes is going to is representing
a neuron and within the neuron there are
two steps. First you compute an aphine
function of the inputs basically a
weighted sum of all the inputs plus a
bias which is captured by this extra
input of one and that aine term is then
put through an activation. So let me
label all my variables. These are all
the weights using the notation that I
just saw earlier show used earlier where
the zero input to any layer is the same
as the bias term. That's just for
simplifying the notation. Instead of
having a separate bias, I just have a
weight going to an additional input
that's pegged at one. And then the first
term that you compute always is the
aphine term. So the aine term has this
notation where if I say z
you know 41
it means it's the alphine term computed
at the fourth neuron in the first layer
that aline term goes into an activation
function and then I have the y's and
then if I say y41
that represents the output of the
activation basically the output of the
neuron itself this is the output of the
fourth neuron in the first layer. So, is
this notation making sense to all of you
guys?
This notation clear to everyone.
Okay. So, all right. And now the output
of the network is compared to the
desired output of the network and we
compute a divergence. Our job is to find
out the derivative of this divergence
with respect to some weight. Say this
guy. Basically, we want to find out how
much is perturbing this little guy over
here perturb the divergence out here.
And there's a big distance between this
guy and this guy. And in between there
are a bunch of variables. You have the
Z's, you have the intermediate Z's and
the intermediate Y's. So all of these
have to be computed in order to be able
to for you to be able to compute the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to this guy. So in the first
step
you know so computation of this
derivative of the divergence with
respect to any input requires
intermediate
output values and the final output value
y itself
because as you know the derivative is
dependent on the location at which you
compute it. So if the y changes the d
the derivative will change because the
derivative is the divergence is a
function of y and so we need to compute
all these intermediate values first
before you can compute the derivative of
this divergence with respect to any
weight. So in the first pass of
computing these derivatives, we are
first going to pass the input through
the network to compute the output of the
network itself. And in the process,
you're going to compute all these
intermediate variables. This is what we
will call the forward pass. We're going
to call it as a forward pass because
you're passing the input forward through
the network to compute the output.
And once you compute the forward pass,
that's when we'll compute the
derivatives.
And how is the forward pass computed?
So the that's very simple. I'm going to
say y superscript 0 is the input. The
input is the zeroth layer. And again, I
don't have an explicit bias. I just have
an extra one over here. And the weight
corresponding to this one is the bias.
This is just for convenience. So I can
simplify my slides. Otherwise you could
have an explicit bias. And so here's
what we do.
Starting from the input, say for the
very first neuron of the first layer,
you'd compute the aphine term. And the
aphine term is going to be the weighted
sum of all of these guys. So the aphine
term at the first neuron of the first
layer is going to be the sum over all
inputs of
the i if input sum over all i's of the i
if input which is y i superscript zero
the superscript zero indicates that it's
the input multiplied by the weight which
connects the iat input to the first
neuron. So this is the weight of the
ayat input to the first neuron. And
these weights are specific to the first
layer. Is this notation clear to
everybody?
The arithmetic that we just performed
over here. Is that clear?
Right. Can I see a few more guesses?
Why the bias is not sound? The bias is I
have an extra input of one. And so this
input the weight of this input is the
bias. Christian that answer
right so
okay so here we are right and using this
formula I can now compute the weights
for these these aine terms for all these
neurons
why zero scripts the zero superscript
means it's the input
that's all it's a zero layer okay that's
just a notation so we can now compute
the alphine terms for all of these
neurons Now these aine terms can just be
put through these activation functions
to compute the y terms for all the
neurons.
And then at the next step I can use the
same formula except now I'd be using the
weights for the second layer as
indicated by the superscript 2 to
compute the aine terms for all of the
neurons and then subsequently I can put
those guys through the second layers
activations to compute all these Y's and
then these Y's. What would I do next
with these V's? Just help me along.
What's the next step guys? If I got this
far, what's the next step?
Anyone?
What is the next step from here?
Help me. And please be the halfine term,
right? I'm going to compute the Z3s
using the same formula. Same as before.
And then those things are going to be
put through the activation. And I'm
going to keep doing this until I finally
get the output of the final layer of the
network.
So this is the forward pass. I'm going
to be going through all the layers. So K
going from one to N. K represents the
layer over here. Within each layer, I'm
going to go over all the neurons. So I'm
going to go over the layer width. So
again, Y0 is the input, right? So I'm
going to go through the layer width and
at each layer, I'm going to compute the
AI terms which are weighted sums of the
outputs of the previous layer. And then
finally, I apply the activation to these
a terms to get the outputs of the
neurons. Just this little loop is going
to compute the output of the network. So
this is this uh algorithm clear for
everybody. This is very simple.
Is this clear?
Yes. Now,
okay guys, just be prompt because this
will take up time, right? I'm going to
check I'll check for questions. So once
we've done so here is a pseudo code this
is the forward pass I have some
three-dimensional input so I'm going to
say y superscript zero is the input for
all the components and I'm going through
the layers within each layer uh so what
is the win notation
the the w okay this is the w i j n is
the weight connecting the iat neuron of
the n minus one layer to the j neuron of
the nth layer and the superscript is the
layer index
that answer your question row one.
Okay. So, and so this is the pseudo
code. You can just go through the pseudo
code. It's exactly what we saw before.
And so, now we've computed all of these
intermediate variables. We must remember
them because we need them to compute the
derivatives. And now we're going to go
backwards. The output of the network is
compared to the desired output of the
network, which gives you the divergence.
And so then from the divergence the way
I'm going to compute the derivative if I
want the derivative of this weight with
respect to the divergence I'm just
asking how much does perturbing this guy
perturb this guy to compute it I'll
first say how much does perturbing this
guy perturb this guy how much does
perturbing this guy perturb this guy and
how does this you know and so how can I
compute how much perturbing this guy
perturbs this guy then I'll take a step
back how much does perturbing this guy
perturb this guy I have to keep working
my way backwards. So I'll first compute
my derivative of the divergence with
respect to the output of the network.
Then the aphine terms here. Then I'm
going to compute the derivatives for all
of these weights. Then the derivatives
for these guys. Then these aine terms,
these weights. Take a step back, compute
the derivatives for these outputs and so
on until I work my way all the way back
to the very first layer of the network.
This is the order in which we're going
to be performing our computation.
Okay, any questions on this so far,
guys? Does this make sense?
The the process did this make sense?
Okay, and the reason we're going to go
backwards uh is that's the only way
that's how we can compute the chain
rule. You need each derivative before
you can compute the next one. And so
because we're going backwards, we call
this back propagation. Let's actually
let's actually see the map. So here is
the entire network.
First I'm assuming that the divergence
function is given and the divergence
function is differentiable. We assumed
this in the last class which means that
if I com if I can get the divergence for
any input using the appropriate formula
for that divergence function. I can get
the derivatives for the of the
divergence with respect to the outputs
of the network. So this guy the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to this guy is given right now
I'm going to apply
uh the chain rule. So Bruno just hang on
till the end of the portion and you can
ask it again right and the rule I'm
going to apply is this very simple one.
If l= f of y where y = g of z then dl /
dz is simply dl / dy * dy / dz. Right?
This is the chain rule that we just saw.
So applying this over here I have dl /
dy.
But then if I want to get the the d the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to y. So if I want to get the
respect to z, I just multiply the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to y, which is this guy,
by the derivative of y with respect to
z, which is this guy. I'm just using
this rule over here. That make sense to
everybody?
Did this make sense?
Right? Very simple. Nothing nothing
complicated. And so here this guy is
already is already available because we
computed that in the first step. What is
the second term? What is the second term
over here? This one. What is this term?
What is this term? Anybody?
What is it? The derivative of the
activation function. And so that's just
the derivative of the activation
function. And that that derivative has
to be computed at a specific ZV valueue.
But that ZV valueue is computed at the
forward pass. And so I just replace this
term by the derivative of the activation
function at the Z that we already have.
So now I have the derivatives of the
divergence with respect to these guys.
Next step, I want to compute the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to say this weight. Using the
chain rule as before, the derivative of
the divergence with respect to the the
weight over here is going to be the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to the Z times the derivative of
Z with respect to this weight. Right?
This is the formula.
Is everybody okay with this formula?
Yes.
Yes. Okay. And which of these terms do
we already have?
There are two terms we Which of these do
Anyone? Which one? Which one do we
already have?
We already have this guy, right? What
about this guy? What is this one?
What is this one here?
Anyone? What is that?
That's the previous Y, right? This is
just computed. We know that y
equals the the z over here is the
weighted sum of all of these y's. The
contribution of this partic particular y
is to is the product of this y by this
weight. So this z is going to be this y
times this weight plus a bunch of other
terms. So the derivative of the z with
respect to w is just going to be the
one, right? And so I can just replace
this by the one. Did this formula make
sense to everybody? Did this make sense
to everyone?
Yes or no?
Okay. And so
good. And so we got this. And so now I
can compute the derivatives for all of
these weights using the same formula.
The derivative for any weight is going
to be the derivative for the Z at the
output of the weight times the input to
the edge.
So finally we need to compute the
derivatives for these guys, right? And
for the derivatives for these guys,
we're going to use the distributed
chain. Remember if I have L= F of many
Z's and each of these Z's is a function
of some X then the derivative of L with
respect to X is the sum over all Z's
of the product of the derivative of L
with respect to Z and the derivative of
Z with respect to X. So either salad
what did you not understand as something
being equal to one
this term is this what you didn't
understand
no but we are looking at this I'm
speaking of this term
I'm saying this guy is going to be
using
okay the derivative is y right you see
this one
this a lot is that making sense sense.
So what is the derivative of Z with
respect to W?
Why? Right. Exactly.
So
and so now let's go back to this one.
Look at this Y. So remember if X relates
to L through many connections, you have
to sum over all the connections for the
derivative, right? this y
influences the divergence through two
connections. So to compute the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to y, we have to sum over both
edges. And the term we have to sum is
the derivative of the divergence with
respect to this z of with respect to
this z times the derivative of the z
with respect to this y plus the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to this z time the derivative of
this z with respect to this y. Is this
formula making sense to everybody?
This one?
Yes. No.
Okay. And
so I see like three or four yeses. Can I
get a few more yeses?
Otherwise, I fear I'm dismissing losing
all of you guys. And
over here we already have the derivative
of the divergence with respect to Z
because we're going backwards. Correct?
So that leaves us with the derivative of
Z with respect to Y. But then again we
know that Z equals
W Y the for any particular Yi the Z
equals that Yi times the corresponding
weight plus other terms. So this Z is
going to be this by I times this weight
plus the contributions of all of these
other terms. So the derivative of this Z
with respect to this Y is simply going
to be this weight as seen from this
formula. Right?
That making sense to everybody?
And so I can just plug this W right
here. And so the derivative of the
divergence with respect to this Y is
summing over all Z's. The derivative of
the divergence with respect to Z times
the weight. Similar, right? And I can
use the same formula to compute the
derivatives for all these bars. Did this
make sense? How I computed the
derivatives for the divergence with
respect to all the weights? Is this
formula making sense to you guys? Yes or
no?
Right?
Nothing complicated about it at all.
It's very very simple, right? And so
then I can use the same chain rule to
get the derivative of the Z divergence
with respect to these Z's. I just
multiply the derivative of the
divergence of S with respect to this Y
by the derivative of this activation
function. And so I get the derivatives
for these Z's. Then I can use the same
formula as before
to compute the derivatives for these
valves. And then I can multiply the
derivatives, right?
So
yeah, and again I have the derivatives
for these weights. The derivative for
the weight is simply going to be the y
times the derivative for z, right? And
then I can go back and compute the
derivatives for the y's. Then I can
compute the derivatives for these aine
terms using the chain rule. I can keep
working my way back until I get all the
way to the derivatives for the weights
for the first layer, which is simply
going to be, you know, the derivative
for any weight is going to be the
corresponding input times the derivative
for the fi at the end of the edge. So
did this. So the overall uh derivative
rule can be written like this. I can say
initially I compute the derivative of
the divergence with respect to the
output of the network.
Then I can multiply those derivatives by
the derivatives for these activation
functions to compute the derivatives for
these Z's. That's my first step.
Then
subsequently
I just go through this very simple step
at each point to compute the derivatives
for these y's. I just take a weighted
sum of the derivatives for these z's.
The derivatives of the y's is just a
weighted sum for the derivatives for the
z's. The derivative for the z is simply
the derivative of the y times the
derivative of the activation function.
And then finally the derivative for any
weight is simply the input to the weight
times the derivative for the Z. And so
if you just loop back using this
equation, you should get the derivatives
not only for all the intermediate
variables but also for all the
parameters in the network. So did this
make sense to everybody. Did this make
sense? Did this whole process? Yes. No.
Right.
So I see that. Can I get it like 30 eyes
so I can move on? I have 15
a few more thumbs up if I may because
I'm just going to jump.
So Christian, what portion of it was
complex over here
just a bit?
Anything that was complicated?
I'm assuming that you know it just needs
review. Let me move on. Right. So I can
actually write the backward pass. I've
just written the code down. But the
reason I wrote the code down is for some
to show something very interesting.
The derivative for the weight for the
output of the neuron is a weighted sum
of the derivatives for the Z's. And also
the derivative for the Z is the
derivative for the Y
times the derivative of the activation.
This entire code looks a lot like the
forward pass. The only extra thing is
this term which is the derivative for
the weight itself. So if you don't
believe me, let me compare this to the
forward pass. Here's what we had in the
forward pass. At each step, the Z was
computed as a weighted sum of the
outputs of the previous layer. And then
the Y was computed by applying an
activation function to the Z. Here the
derivative is computed as a weighted sum
of the uh variables in the next layer
and then you multiply that by the
derivative of the activation function.
Does it do you see the similarity
between these two operations?
Right? In one you're going from left to
right and the other you're going from
right to left but otherwise they're very
similar. The only extra term is the
derivative for the weight itself. So the
whole thing is really really really
really simple. You know the network
looks really scary but then when you
actually write out the rules the
derivative rules are trivial
and we'll see in a bit how they can be
even more trivial. Right? So I'm going
to give you 30 seconds for this question
because I need the time.
Okay, 15 seconds, guys.
15 seconds. 5 seconds.
Okay, let me end this one. So, does
anybody want to answer this question?
Which is it?
B. The answer is C.
Back propagation is the method used to
compute derivatives.
It does not deal with training. It's
entirely about computing derivatives. We
use those derivatives in gradient
descent to update model parameters. But
back propagation itself is not gradient
descent. Back propagation is just the
procedure we use to compute derivatives.
That clear to everybody
yes.
Yes. Understand? It gives you a
derivative with respect to again see
when I draw the network in this manner
this weight is just the bias. So you're
going to get the derivative for the bias
as well. The answer you understand?
Yeah. Okay. And so here we are. Right
now there are some special cases. So far
I've assumed that the computation of one
neuron doesn't affect the computation of
the other neurons. If I apply an
activation to this Z, it modifies this
Y. It doesn't modify these Y's.
But we also compute the assume that the
aphine term input to any neuron is an
aphine combination. It's a weighted
addition. We're also assuming that the
activations are differentiable. We made
all of these assumptions. Not all of
them may be true. So let's look at some
special cases. Vector activations. In
your scalar activations, if you modified
this Z, only this Y changed.
In a vector activation, if I modify the
Z, all of these Y's could change. Can
somebody give me an example of an
activation which does this?
Someone can you give me that's a soft
max, right? So, uh, and
so in the case of scalar activations,
each y is a function of just the z and
vector activations, this vector of y's
is a function of this vector of z's.
then our depend influence diagrams
break. So in your scalar case each Z
influences only the corresponding Y. In
the vector case this Z influences this Y
but it also influences all the other Ys.
How will this change the back
propagation rule? Anybody can you tell
me how this will change the back
propagation rule?
How will it change it? someone
summation right because what happens is
when I'm using your standard derivative
the derivative of the divergence with
respect to z is the derivative of the
divergence with respect to y * dy / dz
but over here this z influences all
these y's and all these y's influence
the divergence so the derivative of the
divergence with respect to z must sum
over all of these dies. It's going to be
the sum over all y's of the derivative
of the divergence with respect to y
times the derivative of y with respect
to z, right? And so that means that you
know and this so you know special case
of the softmax each y exponentiates the
z and then normalizes to one. So when
you modify the z the z modifies all
these y's they influence the divergence.
So the derivative of the divergence with
respect to z sums over all the y's of
the derivative of the divergence with
respect to y times the derivative of the
y with respect to z. And furthermore
this means you need the derivative of
each of these y's with respect to z. Now
for the through case remember the
softmax is basically a an instance of a
sigmoid. So when y is very close to one
or when y is very close to zero one or
zero this derivative is going to be zero
and in the middle it's going to be the
largest so that this formula makes
sense. It's y * 1 - y for this through
line.
Also
note that this derivative is always
positive. Okay, which means that which
makes sense. If you increase Z, this Y
will increase. Correct?
Increasing Z increases this Y. And so
you can see this term is always
positive. Yes or no?
If I increase the Z, what will happen to
this Y?
Will it increase or decrease?
And so it sure indeed it should reduce,
right? And so you can see the
derivatives for these guys are negative
and they are proportional to both this y
and this y. Basically accounting for the
fact is this that if either of them are
saturated. Uh why does it decrease?
Because if I increase this y see this y
increases the y sum to one. So the rest
of them must decrease. That answer your
question
right? So
and so uh that also gets all the other
derivatives
and then we look at so we looked at
vector activations there are other
vector activations on the slide please
look them up right now let's look at
non-ifferiable activations the relu is
the relu differentiable
everywhere is the rel differentiable
everywhere
not at zero right so but what happens at
zero is continuous, right? When you have
things like this add zero, you can't
have the derivative. So, you use
something called subgradians. Now,
remember the reason we want the
derivative is to find out which
direction to move in to guarantee that
the function always increases. So, at
this point, I can draw a bunch of lines.
If the line intersects the function,
then I really can't tell you anything
about what's happening to the function
itself because the function is below the
line. So the slope of this line doesn't
tell me anything about the behavior of
the function. But if I choose any line
that just touches
the function like so then these guys for
any of these lines if I use the
corresponding slope the function is
always going to increase because the
function always lies above the line at
this point. Is this making sense to you
guys?
Right? Is this making sense to you guys?
And so you can use the slopes of any of
these lines as your derivative. But
there's a better way of looking at it.
How's that? I can just assume that this
guy
actually does this.
That the net the function actually
changes continuously just rotates
instantaneously from here to here. So
this function at this point has every
slope between 0 and one because the line
is rotating at that one point. And so if
I use any slope between 0 and one,
that's a valid slope at this point. And
I can use this in gradient descent. Is
this making sense?
Yes or no? Right.
Okay. So what was the question here?
So you say this at point z every
everything between zero and one.
>> Yes. So you can think of this as a
function. You can think of this as a
function instead of doing this.
It's doing this very quickly just at
this one point. Right? If you look at
this guy, it has every slope between
zero and one. Right? Yes or no?
>> Yes. If it does it very quickly all at
one point at that one point every slope
between 0 and one is still valid right.
>> Yes
>> that's what we mean. So for the relu you
can use any slope between 0 and one.
Typically we'll use one because we want
the uh fastest descent. Okay. For the
max there's a different property.
Suppose I have an activation function
which considers all of these Z's and
always returns the maximum Z. Right? So
suppose I have Z I have these four Z's
and they are 1 3 5 and 7. What is the
output of the max activation for this
guy? What will the output be?
Seven. Right? If I perturb this guy,
will this output change?
If I put out the one, will the output
change?
So what is the derivative of the output
with respect to this guy?
Zero. How about the derivative with
respect to this guy?
0.
What about the output with respect to
this guy?
If I perturb it, will the output change?
One. Right? And so the derivative is
going to be one with respect to the
largest
element in the set and zero everything
else with respect to everything else.
And so here is your third pole.
15 seconds, guys.
5 seconds.
Let me end this here.
Okay.
So Sean, I'll get I'll get you there in
a minute. But which are the correct ones
here? Can somebody tell me which are the
correct ones here?
B, D, and E. Right. Perfect. If you have
multiple of them having the same value,
perturbing either of them is going to
increase the output. So both of them can
use a derivative of one. That answer
your question, Sha?
So if I have 377
whether I put up this or this the output
is going to put up the same amount. So
the derivatives for both these guys is
one.
Okay.
Beautiful. And so in our backward pass
in the pseudo code these derivatives
might actually be subgradients. And so
the overall approach is for each data
instance in the forward pass the
instance through the net store all
intermediate outputs in the backward
pass sweep back through the net
iteratively compute all derivatives with
respect to all the weights. The actual
loss is the sum as the average of the
divergence over all training instances
not the sum and the actual gradient is
the sum is the as the average of the
derivatives for all the training
instances. We're going to use that in
our gradient descent rule. Okay, so
pseudo code over here, it's going to
have two passes.
You're going to initialize the weights.
You initialize the loss. Then you for
each training instance, you perform a
forward pass, push it through the net,
and get all intermediate values. You do
a backward pass, go backwards and
compute all the derivatives. then you
average all the derivatives and
uh you increment the parameter by the
average derivative because that is the
derivative of the overall loss. So is
this process clear to everybody?
Right.
Fantastic. Exactly. Right.
So,
right. And
now we're going to jump into some magic.
If you did it the way I just explained,
you'd have to write lots and lots of
loops. Right. For layered networks, it's
generally simpler to think of the
process in terms of vector operations
because the arithmetic is much simpler.
You can use fast matrix libraries
especially in GPUs which makes things
much faster and we can restate the
entire process in vector terms this
which is what you use in any real system
and the math becomes trivially trivially
simple. So if you don't believe me,
consider one layer over here. This is
one layer. These y's are used to compute
these aphine terms, right? And to
compute this aine term, I have a weight
with respect to each of these y's.
Let me do something. Let me put all of
these y's into a vector. I'm calling
this y k to say this is the out vector
of outputs of the kth layer. Is this
notation clear, guys? Is this notation
clear?
Yes or no?
Similarly, let me take all of these Z's
and put them into a vector. I'm going to
call this ZK. ZK is the Z value. So,
this YK is actually this one is the
vector of these Y's. Okay? Because it's
a K layer. ZK is the vector of these
guys. Is this notation clear?
Okay. And now if I I'm going to write a
weight matrix W
the subscript K meaning it's the weight
matrix for the K layer. Right? Now the
weights for all of the or the set all
the weights for the first neuron
will be the first layer of this matrix.
All the weights for the second neuron
will be the second layer of this matrix.
All the weights for the nth neuron will
be the nth layer of this matrix.
Is this notation clear?
Yes. No. Okay. Now let's see what
happens. I have suppose I take y k minus
one, right?
That's going to be for the k layer. It's
going to be y1 y2 blah. And then if I
multiply this by the W, this W is going
to be the weight for the first neuron,
the weight for the W21,
W31 and so on. This product is going to
be W11 * Y1
plus W
* Y2
and so on. So you're going to get a
weighted sum of all of these guys. Just
the first entry. I'm looking at the
first entry. If I multiply these two
matrices, the result is going to be a
first vector. Right? What is this first
guy? This weight times this first first
y plus this weight time the second y
plus this weight time this third y and
so on.
I know the screen looks horrible, but
did this make sense that if I multiply
this W and this Y, it's going to be this
weight time this Y plus this weight time
this Y and so on plus this weight time
this Y, right? And then if I add the B's
on top of it, then you're going to end
up with a very simple formula. ZK = W K
* YKUS 1 + BK
It's not a square matrix. The matrix is
going to have as many columns as the Y's
is going to be have as many rows as the
Z's.
That answer your questions here?
Yeah. Okay. Those these weights, okay,
the weights of this first neuron are the
first row.
Okay.
So when I multiply this guy, let's say y
k minus one. So these are all the k
minus one clear. That's going to be the
first weight, this guy,
times the first entry, which is this
guy, right? Plus the second weight, this
guy,
times the second entry, which is this
guy, and so on. So the product of these
two of the W and this Y K the first
entry is just going to be the weighted
sum of these parts with the appropriate
weights that answer your question
you bet
it's okay and then of course you have
the bias and so I can just write this
rule this way and now these Y's can just
be put through the activation function F
these Z's can be put through the
activation function F to get the Ys
Right.
So,
uh, the weight matrix notation doesn't
match the usual matrix notation. That's
because it's Yeah, I'm saying W11
because it's the weight from the first
neuron to the first neuron. W21
because it's a weight from the second
neuron to the first neuron. Right? W1 is
this guy. This is W21. Right, Anderson?
This will be W31. And so that's why we
have these. That clarify?
Yes. No. Okay. All right. And so once I
can just write it this way.
The forward pass is extremely simple.
Here's what I do. I just set my Y0 to X.
Y1. Z1 is just W1 Y 0 + B1.
Y1 is just F_sub_1 applied to Z1.
Z2 is just W2 Y1 + B2.
Y2 is just F_sub_2 applied to Z2 and so
on. I can go all the way to the end of
the network. Then answer. So this is the
entire forward computation. This is so
much simpler when you look at it than
the code that we wrote for when we were
writing loops. In the vector notation, I
just set y0 to be equal to x. Then I
loop through the layers within each
layer. I just compute the z as wy + b
and then compute y as the activation
applied to z. And the output of the
network is of course the output of the
final layer. Did this make sense to
everybody? How this is really really
simple?
This makes sense to everyone,
right? Why do we consider the bias
explicitly? You don't need to. I just
wrote it out explicitly. That's all.
Again, notation, right? I just wanted to
uh I
earlier I didn't have the bias
separately because writing loops is
painful. But then when I write it in
vector notation, it's much straight
part. So I just have the bias explicit.
That's all.
So this is the forward pass, right? Ykus
one is the output of the previous layer.
So having computed the forward pass,
we're going to do the backward pass. But
for the backward pass, we're going to
use a little more calculus, but vector
calculus this time. And here is the
amazing thing. It doesn't matter whether
you're dealing with scalers or vectors.
Once you begin using influence diagrams,
the same rules apply. So if y is a
scalar or if I have y equals f of z,
right? Then we have delta y equals the
derivative of y with respect to z* delta
z. We said this was the only acceptable
notation for derivatives. Remember? Yes.
No
this guy. Remember this guys?
And so I can write this influence
diagram exactly the same as before. I
can say Z influences Y and the term on
top of the edge is the derivative of Y
with respect to Z.
Let's see how this simplifies again. Is
this clear everybody? Yes. No.
I'm going to use this to fly through.
Right.
Okay.
The kids in India, is this clear?
at least some of you. Okay.
All right. So, let's see how this helps
me.
If I have a vector function of a vector
variable, this derivative is what is
called this. If if it's a scalar
function of a vector variable, this is a
standard derivative. Remember, if the
variable Z is a column vector, what was
the what was the derivative? If Z was a
column vector, what was this derivative?
What was this guy? If y is a scalar,
what was this guy? Anybody? What was
this? If Z is a column vector,
this was a row vector, right?
Okay. And so
if Y is a vector
and Z is a vector, then the derivative
of Y with respect to Z is called a
Jacobian.
And what does the Jacobian look like?
The key over here is to realize that
when y is a vector, I can think of it as
a vertical stacking of many scalar
functions.
This make sense? If y is a vector, I can
think of it as a vertical stacking of
many scalar functions. That make sense?
Yes. No.
So
the derivative of y with respect to z,
what do you think it's going to be?
What is it going to be?
It's a vertical stacking of the
derivatives of the individual y's with
respect to z.
And the derivative for any individual y
is a row vector. And so this jacobian is
simply a vertical stacking of the
derivatives for the individual y with
respect to z. That make sense to
everybody?
Yes. No.
Right.
Rest of you guys.
Okay.
So easy, right?
Now the Jacobians can describe
derivatives with respect to their input
even if you have scalar activations. I
can think of this as a vector activation
where the where the jaccoian is just a
diagonal
because perturbing this Z will not
perturb this Y. Right? So only the
diagonal entries are going to be non
zero. The rest of them will be zero.
Whereas if I have a vector activation
then the Jacobian matrix is going to be
a full matrix. Does this make sense?
Then it applies in both cases. It just
changes the nature of the Jacobian.
Yes. No.
Okay. Very simple. Okay.
And so
special case aphine functions. For aine
functions I have Z = Wy + V. Right. What
is the derivative of y at z with respect
to y?
So if I perturb y by a delta by a small
delta. So if I say y + delta y
* w * + b is simply going to be w y + b
plus w delta y. Correct? Which means if
I write the output as Z z + delta z
then delta z is simply going to be wz
delta y which means that the jacobian of
z with respect to y is simply going to
be w
that make sense to everybody
everybody yes no
okay and of course z is just directly
b is just being directly added to we get
Z. So the derivative of Z with respect
to B is just the identity matrix. This
jacobian is the identity matrix.
Everybody good with this so far?
Yes. No.
Give me a few yeses so I can Okay. And
now
chain rule. This is very important.
Please keep track. Right. If I have Y
equals some function Y of Z of X, X
influences Z, Z influences Y. Right?
This h has the derivative of z with
respect to x. This h has the derivative
of y with respect to z. So I have delta
the derivative of y
with respect to x
is going to be the derivative of y with
respect to z times the derivative of z
with respect to x. And uh to see how
this works, you can actually work out
the math. You can see that I can say
delta y equals delta z times the
derivative of y with respect to z *
delta z. But delta z is the is the
derivative of z with respect to x *
delta x. So plugging this guy
in over here gives me delta y equals the
derivative of y with respect to z times
the derivative of z with respect to x
time delta x. Okay, observe the order
which came first and which came second?
Which came first and which came second?
Anybody?
Outer first. Right. This came first.
This came second. Can I change the
order?
If I change the order, the math breaks
down. Right?
So as you go back,
the newer derivatives always get
multiplied to the right.
Is that clear to everybody?
Right. Okay. So, fantastic. Now, suppose
I have an extended chain rule. X
influences Z1 influences Y1 influences
Z2 influences Y2 influences D. How do I
compute the derivative of D
uh with respect to say Y2 Z2 Y1 Z1 X.
First,
I'm going to have so if D was your
divergence, I'm going to have the
derivative of the divergence with
respect to Y2. Right? Then I'm going to
take a step back and I'm going to
multiply the derivative of the
divergence with respect to Y2 by the
derivative of Y2 with respect to Z2. So
at this point, I have the derivative of
D with respect to Z2. Then I'm going to
take a step back
and I'm going to multiply the derivative
of since at this point I have the
derivative of d with respect to z2
I'm going to multiply the derivative of
d with respect to z2 right multiply it
by the derivative of z2 with respect to
y1
and so that gives me the derivative of d
with respect to y1 and now at this point
I have the derivative of d with respect
to y1 I write multip multiply it by the
derivative of Y1 with respect to Z and
then I get the derivative of with
respect to Z1 and then I can right
multiply that by the derivative of Z1
with respect to X and that gives me the
derivative with respect to X. Observe
that as each time as you take keep going
going back you're just right multiplying
by the latest derivative. Did that make
sense to everybody?
Yes. No.
Awesome. Right. So simple.
One last case. If I have the derivative
if z = w y + b and some and d is f of z.
Then if I want the derivative of d with
respect to this w
that it turns out is going to be y * the
derivative of d with respect to z. Okay.
And the der uh actually
wait this was
the derivative of d with respect to y is
going to be the derivative of d with
respect to z * w. This is easy just
straight up right. The derivative of d
with respect to b is simply going to be
the derivative of d with respect to z
because z and b have the same variable.
But the crazy bit is the derivative of d
with respect to w.
And the derivative of D with respect to
W, it turns out, is going to be
Y, the input to this connection, times
the derivative of D with respect to Z.
And if you work it out, you will see
that the size is pi. So let's say Y is
an N component column vector. Let's say
Y is an N component column vector. Z is
an M component column vector. D is a
scalar. What is the derivative of D with
respect to Z?
What is this going to be? What is the
shape?
What is the shape of the derivative of D
with respect to Z?
Come on, guys.
It's 1 + M, right? But what is what is W
going to be? W is going to be
n
M cross N right
because N inputs and M outputs. What is
the derivative of D with respect to W
going to be? What is the shape?
What is the derivative of D with respect
to W going to be? Anyone
remember the derivatives are always the
same shape as the transpose of the
variable. So the derivative of D with
respect to W is going to be N cross M.
This making sense? Yes. No.
Right. And so let's check this guy. Y is
N + 1, right?
Derative of D with respect to Z is 1 +
M. So the result is N cross M.
The shape is right. Is this making sense
that this formula is right
everybody? Clear? Give me a yes or no?
Okay. And so now I'm just going to take
this and fly. Right. So the derivative
of a scala with respect to an n cross
one vector is 1 + n. With respect to an
n cross n matrix is n cross n. So if z
is n cross one and y is n cross one. and
cross one you find that the derivative
is the correct size right
and that's because the derivatives of
the transit. So we have the derivatives
of the divergence with respect to both V
and W. Now we're all set, right? So this
applies for any layer of the network.
Let me actually skip this uh next couple
of slides. We're going to apply this
straight to a network. But first
actually, yeah, I'll let you take a shot
at this before I
uh
do the last few minutes of the lecture.
So what do you mean by why does Y come
first?
The outermost come. So, okay, in in the
derivative with respect to W, the math
is a little more complicated because
you're speaking of the derivative with
respect to the edge, the weights. And
so, I just showed you that the size
works out. If you want to actually go
through the math, post on Piaza and I'll
show you why it comes out that way.
Okay,
that's a very good question, Aki.
Okay, five seconds guys, otherwise I run
out of time.
All right, let me stop here.
Anybody want to answer this question?
I have B, right? Because I have X
influencing H influencing G influencing
Y. So if I go backwards, the derivative
of y with respect to x is going to be
the derivative of y, which is f, right?
f with respect to g time the derivative
of g with respect to h time the
derivative of h with respect to x. So
this is the correct one going back. This
make sense to everyone?
Yes. All right. And so let's move on. So
here's the network again. Here are all
the variables from X you compute the
first aine term from which you compute
Y1 for each layer you first compute the
AI term and then the output and finally
get the output of the network you put
that through a divergence function you
get the divergence here is the influence
diagram right X influences Z1 influences
Y1 and so on this picture making sense
this influence diagram yes no
okay So
I'm I'm going to use this Nabla
notation, right? So
why is this not making sense? X is
influencing Z1, right? Z1 is influencing
Y1 and so on.
That clarify?
Okay. If it didn't, we'll just do this
after class. Okay. Now on each edge I'm
just going to put the derivative for the
edge which is the derivative of the
output of the edge with respect to the
input. Okay.
Now let's look at these guys. What is
the derivative of any z with respect to
the previous y? What is the derivative
of any z with respect to the previous y
guys?
What is that?
W right? And what is the derivative of
any y with respect to the z?
What is the derivative of any y with
respect to the z?
Come on guys, that's quick.
Those are jacobians, right?
The those are the jacobians of the
activation function. And so these guys
are weights.
And so here is the final influence
diagram. weight jacobian weight jacobian
weight jacobian weight jacobian and so
on and so when I compute the derivatives
going back first I have the derivative
with respect to the out here because I
assume this divergence function is
differentiable then to compute the
derivative with respect to z right
multiply by the derivative of y with
respect to z which is the jacob
then to compute the derivative with so I
have the derivative at this point then I
need the derivative with respect to the
W.
Uh so I need if I wanted to compute the
derivative with respect to Y, I just
right multiply the derivative of the
divergence with the weight of this H
which is just the weight. So that gives
me the derivative with respect to this
Y. Right? And then finally
again this is computed. This is the Q
term. I also need the derivatives for
these parameters.
But then we already have the rule. The
derivative for the weight matrix is the
input which is y times the derivative
for z. We s saw this earlier. So we have
this and the derivative for b is simply
the derivative for z. So is this formula
making sense?
This guy is this making sense?
Yes. No. I'm going to go over by a
couple of minutes. Right? So, I need you
guys to reply. Okay, there's like two
yeses, but I'm moving it. I'm assuming
it represents everybody. And so, I can
keep continuing this going backwards.
All I'm doing is that as I go back the
chain at each point, I'm just right
multiplying by the derivative on the
latest edge. And so, here is my overall
back propagation rule. I just first
start off with the derivative of the
divergence with respect to y. Then as I
keep going back at each point I first
right multiply by the jacobian then I
write multiply by the weight. Then I go
back and write multiply by the jacobian
and I right multiply by the weight and
for each layer the derivative for the
bias is simply the derivative for z. The
derivative for the weights is y * the
derivative for z. And so that gives me
this entire backward pass. I first
you know I as I'm going to get the
derivative with respect to the output of
the network and then I go back and at
each layer I multiply the derivative for
Y by the Jacobian to get the derivative
for Z and then the derivative for Z by
the weight to get the derivative for the
previous Y and the derivative for W is
just Y * the derivative for Z derivative
for B is just the derivative for Z
that's the entire trading algorithm. And
so just coming to the end, if I'm
setting up the overall process, if I'm
setting up for digit recognition, for
example, I'm going to have my training
data as we saw before. For
classification, you use KL divergence.
For if this is a binary classifier for
multiclass classification, this would
use a softmax output with KL divergence.
And then you just use this very simple
straight up back propagation algorithm
forward and backward algorithm to
compute all derivatives within the
gradient descent loop. So that's the end
of the lecture uh topics. How well does
it learn? Does the procedure really
converge? Will it generalize outside
training data? What does the output
really mean? We will address these in
future classes. Okay. So, I'll stop
right here with apologies for going over
two minutes.